<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Account of the secret services of Monsieur de Vernay, the French minister at Ratisbonne to Count Teckeley as they pass'd by way of letter, with the cypher and key taken from the original, printed in French at Ratisbonne : together with the speech and memorial of the imperial minister Zorowiski, deliver'd to the King of Poland : to which is added Mercurius panegyricus.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49695</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L57</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27126</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09657803</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09657803</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43935</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49695)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43935)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1334:38)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Account of the secret services of Monsieur de Vernay, the French minister at Ratisbonne to Count Teckeley as they pass'd by way of letter, with the cypher and key taken from the original, printed in French at Ratisbonne : together with the speech and memorial of the imperial minister Zorowiski, deliver'd to the King of Poland : to which is added Mercurius panegyricus.</title>
                  <author>L. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Ratisbonne [Amsterdam?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to L.S.--Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Du Vernay, Boucauld.</term>
               <term>Thököly, Imre, --  gróf, 1657-1705.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="panegyric">
            <pb facs="tcp:43935:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Panegyrick Mercury UPON THE SUCCESSES AGAINST THE TURKS, In the <hi>AUTUMN,</hi> 1683.</p>
            <p>BY the Goodneſs and Bounty of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the XI. By the Councils and Induſtry of the moſt Auguſt Emperor, <hi>Leopold</hi> the I. By the Good Fortune and Diſpatch of <hi>John</hi> the III. King of <hi>Poland.</hi> By the Truth and Bravery of <hi>Maximilian,</hi> Electoral-Duke of <hi>Bavaria.</hi> By the Generoſity and Courage of <hi>John George</hi> the III. Electoral-Duke of <hi>Saxony.</hi> By the Vigilance of <hi>Charles,</hi> Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> in the Field. By the Conſtancy of <hi>Erneſtus,</hi> Count <hi>Staremberg,</hi> within the Walls. In fine, By the Joint Force Of the Fighting Layety, and the Praying Prieſthood. By an admirable Agreement of All in the Beſt Cauſe. With the Aids of CHRIST. Without the Reinforcements of the moſt Chriſtian Prince. Againſt the Anti-Chriſtian. <hi>VIENNA</hi> ſtands Delivered; The <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Power ſtaggers; The Fortune of Rebellion falls; The Gate of <hi>Gran</hi> is Open'd; <hi>Auſtria</hi> ſhines after its Fires, and tryumphs after Fields of Blood; For whom <hi>GOD</hi> alwayes employs Wonders Againſt the Councils of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> and <hi>French.</hi> Dread therefore, ye Enemies, <hi>GOD</hi> Fighting for <hi>Leopold!</hi> Love, ye Subjects, <hi>Leopold,</hi> Fighting for <hi>GOD!</hi> Utter Ruine be your Hope, ye Rebels! Entire Victory yours, our Loyal Friends! For, Let Heaven, and Earth, and Hell be moved, In the End, The Good CAUSE is Crowned.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="panegyric">
            <pb facs="tcp:43935:2"/>
            <head>Mercurius Panegyricus, RERUM CONTRA TURCAS, Geſtarum Autumno Menſe, <hi>Anno,</hi> 1683.</head>
            <l>SAnctitate &amp; Liberalitate Summi Pontificis <hi>Innocentii XI.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Conſilio &amp; Induſtria Auguſtiſſimi Imperatoris <hi>Leopoldi I.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Felicitate &amp; Velocitate <hi>Johannis III.</hi> Regis <hi>Poloniae.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Fidelitate &amp; Magnanimitate <hi>Maximilani</hi> Ducis Electoris <hi>Bavariae.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Generoſitate &amp; Fortittudine <hi>Johannis Georgii III.</hi> Ducis Electoris <hi>Saxoniae.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Vigilantia <hi>Caroli</hi> Ducis <hi>Lotharingiae</hi> in Caſtris.</l>
            <l>Conſtantia <hi>Erneſti</hi> Comitis Starembergi in Muris</l>
            <l>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitis deni<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Viribus Pugnantis Imperii, &amp; Orantis <hi>Sacerdotii;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Admir anda omnium Concordia in optima Cauſa,</l>
            <l>Cum adjutorio CHRISTI.</l>
            <l>Sine auxilio Chriſtianiſſimi.</l>
            <l>Contra Anti-Chriſtianum.</l>
            <l>Stat liberata VIENNA.</l>
            <l>Vacillat Potentia TURCIS.</l>
            <l>Cadit Rebellionis Fortuna;</l>
            <l>Patet <hi>Strigonii</hi> Porta;</l>
            <l>Splendet poſt Incendia, &amp; a Cladibus faelix triumphat <hi>Auſtria;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Pro qua DEUS ſemper facit Mirabilia</l>
            <l>Contra TURCARUM &amp; GALLORUM Conſilia.</l>
            <l>Timete igitur, Hoſtes, pugnantem pro LEOPOLDO DEUM;</l>
            <l>Amate ſubditi, pugnantem pro DEO LEOPOLDUM:</l>
            <l>Cladem ultimam expectate, Rebelles</l>
            <l>Victoriam plenam ſperate, Fideles:</l>
            <l>Nam</l>
            <l>Celum &amp; Terra, &amp; Acheron moveatur,</l>
            <l>Tandem</l>
            <l>Bona CAUSA triumphat.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43935:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43935:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF THE SECRET SERVICES OF <hi>Monſieur de VERNAY</hi> THE <hi>French</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Ratisbonne,</hi> to Count <hi>Teckeley,</hi> as they paſs'd by way of LETTER, with the <hi>Cypher</hi> and <hi>Key</hi> taken from the Original, printed in <hi>French</hi> at <hi>Ratisbonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TOGETHER WITH The Speech and Memorial of the Imperial Miniſter <hi>Zorowiski,</hi> deliver'd to the King of <hi>Poland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is added <hi>MERC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S PANEGYRIC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Galli, ubi</hi> ſolitudinem <hi>fecêrunt,</hi> Pacem <hi>appellant.</hi> 
               <bibl>Tacitus.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>A RATISBONNE MDCLXXXIIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:43935:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43935:4"/>
            <head>A LETTER from Monſieur <hi>S. L.</hi> a <hi>Poliſh</hi> Lord, to Monſieur the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>C. L.</hi> In which are manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcovered the Practices and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Intrigues of the <hi>French</hi> with the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Hungarian</hi> Rebels. With ſome Letters and Remarks upon this Subject.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU have given me ſufficient aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of the continuance of your Friendſhip in the Letter I now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from you, and by the earneſt deſire you expreſs of being informed by me of what our Sentiments are in <hi>Poland,</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the preſent Troubles in <hi>Hungary.</hi> The common report, you ſay, accuſes the French of having raiſed the War with the <hi>Turk;</hi> and making uſe of <hi>Poland</hi> to ſet its Engines at Work, and put in execution its pernicious Deſigns. If you are of the ſame Opinion with our <hi>Polanders,</hi> I ſhall tell you, with my accuſtomed freedom, that you do not wholly wrong them; For it is true that my
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43935:5"/>Country-men, for ſome years paſt have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered themſelves to be over-reacht by the <hi>French,</hi> and that by treating with them too ingenuouſly, they have inſenſibly been drawn in to bear a part with them in their evil Practices; and among others, in favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Malecontents in <hi>Hungary.</hi> They acknowledge at preſent, though perhaps too late, their Errour, and begin to fear leſt they have purchaſed to themſelves Enemies, who after they have filled their own Country with Deſolation, their Ambition and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barity may make them turn their Arms againſt <hi>Poland.</hi> Sir, we love our ſelves, and our Friendſhip cannot conſiſt with thoſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Maximes. Their Politiques appear to us ſo much the more criminal, becauſe there is no juſt revenge, but that which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges us to fight our Enemies with our Arms in our Hands, and openly; nor any ſo baſe, as that which makes us uſe wicked Deviſes, and execrable Treaſons as the Inſtruments of their Ruine. I have a great eſteem for the <hi>Sarmatians,</hi> becauſe they had this good Quality, that they never ſuffered their ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picions to prevail againſt any Mans credit, and that they choſe always rather to judge of others according to their own Inclinations, than upon bare conjectures think them ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43935:5"/>of Malice. And I beg of you, Sir, to afford me the ſame Juſtice, at ſuch time as at the Diet of <hi>Ratisbonne,</hi> you unravel <hi>Pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopes</hi> weaving, and condemn my Countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens wicked Politicks. I grant you, that the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> that by their caballing and Seditiouſneſs have been baniſhed their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, have found in <hi>Poland</hi> both refuge and Friends to protect them. I eaſily alſo acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that the original of all the Evils you complain of, has its riſe from an abuſe of the Liberty that we have in <hi>Germany.</hi> You may alſo reckon up ſo many Factions and Parties, whether in Peace or War, as there are lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Kings, that in theſe laſt Ages have raiſed themſelves to the Royal Authority, and eſtabliſhed their Throne in the midſt of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many.</hi> Now after this, you ought not to be ſurprized to ſee that our Governours have granted the Favour of Hoſpitality to thoſe that complained that their Liberty was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from them in their Country, and that all Laws were violated to oppreſs them in the higheſt degree; ſince humanity it ſelf, and the right of Neighbourhood could not let them refuſe to admit them, till ſuch time as they were reconciled to the Emperour the Sovereign and Maſter. It may yet be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed that the <hi>French</hi> protected them,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43935:6"/>thinking there was ſome merit in protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Miſerable oppreſſed. I am alſo of Opinion, that the <hi>Polanders</hi> were perſuaded to ſuffer among themſelves thoſe that came from <hi>Hungary</hi> baniſhed their Country, and deprived of their Goods, upon thoughts of preſerving them to the Empire and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity; and to the end that their Deſpair might not oblige them to have recourſe to the <hi>Turk,</hi> to obtain his Protection. If it was the <hi>French</hi> Deſign in theſe laſt Wars of <hi>Germany</hi> to draw more buſineſs upon the Emperour, and divide his Forces; it ought to be remembred that we are not to mind in an Enemy either craft, or violence. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, I condemn that way of proceeding, which occaſioned them to bear an Enemies Heart in time of Peace; and have a Horrour at their fomenting the troubles of <hi>Hungary</hi> with their Forces and Counſel. This Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement breaks the moſt ſacred bonds of Friendſhip and Peace. So have I always, and many others with me, thought it very ill that <hi>Frenchmen</hi> ſhould go out of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as it were out of the <hi>Trojan Horſe,</hi> to go as Spies into <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> for to raiſe Troubles, and encourage the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented ſo much the more by giving them Mony and Arms. All <hi>Europe</hi> knows how
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43935:6"/>
               <hi>Bohancy,</hi> the Head of the Rebels of <hi>Tranſylva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> with ſome <hi>French</hi> of the ſame Leven, famous for their Crimes committed in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> run up and down to raiſe Seditions, and join themſelves to the Rebels. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the unviolable obſervance due to ſo ſolemn a Treaty of Peace, made me doubt, whether <hi>France</hi> did Authoriſe this Conduct; and I could no longer fix my Suſpicions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the moſt Chriſtian King, when I reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it has alwayes been fatal to Sovereigns, by many Examples, to reduce Subjects to Revolt, or to maintain or protect them when they have roſe againſt their Lawful Prince. Beſides, I was never ſo bold or raſh as to cry down the Glory of Kings and Sovereigns; and I can ſay, that if Fortune had been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to my Government, having never offended any Body in my life, I ſhould be very happy. The moſt Chriſtian King, by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Succeſs of his Arms, the greatneſs of his Exploits and Victories, has raiſed his Glory to ſo high a Pitch, that he ought on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to uſe it with moderation, and it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs for him to uſe unworthy artifices for to make himſelf more Glorious. Souls truly Royal and Magnanimous, have always de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed the Conqueſts they could more eaſily obtain by Cunning than by force of Arms.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43935:7"/>And it was through this ſentiment, worthy a great Heart, that <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great ſharply rebuked his Favourite <hi>Parmenio,</hi> who would have put him upon a crafty De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, ſaying to him, That it was fit only for Robbers to have recourſe to Treachery, as their only means to compaſs their Thefts. Nevertheleſs, becauſe the Miniſters of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are People more zealous in their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments than they ſhould be, and hold that they may lawfully commit all ſorts of In juſtice for their Sovereign's intereſt, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the ſame time they do their buſineſs; I thought it might poſſibly be the ſame in <hi>France.</hi> The better to aſſure my ſelf in this belief, I would be informed by thoſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, that keep the Bank here of the <hi>French</hi> mony (for we never want ſome <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> who had rather live under the <hi>French</hi> Slavery, than be ſatisfied with the liberty of <hi>Poland</hi>) what great concerns the <hi>French</hi> had with the Duke of <hi>Tranſylvania, Apafiius,</hi> ſo much conſtrained to the <hi>Turks</hi> Party, what were the Deſigns and Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to what end was ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and going of <hi>Akakia, Du Vernay Boucauld,</hi> and all the other Expreſſes.</p>
            <p>At laſt, I found they gave no other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but that the <hi>French</hi> were at preſent in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43935:7"/>Poſſeſſion, and going through all Countrys, that they found every where Friends and Allies; and that they were at laſt arrived at the time of fulfilling the deſire they had long had of ſeeing themſelves Maſters of all the World. This is it theſe <hi>French</hi> Prophets boaſt of, founding their hopes and pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon this ground, that there is no other way of oppoſing the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> which aſpires to the entire Monarchy of all <hi>Europe,</hi> but the <hi>French</hi> King's entring into a League with the <hi>Turk,</hi> and there making an Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and joyning their Forces by vertue of a Treaty, confirmed with an Oath taken upon the Holy <hi>Evangeliſts;</hi> but this you may learn better from the Original; as if it could ever be juſtifiable to revenge one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury with another wrong done to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, and the Deſtruction of our Holy Mother the Church.</p>
            <p>Having asked theſe French-men, what Prince of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> it was that diſturbed <hi>France</hi> for this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy,</hi> they knew not which to name; this makes me believe, that thoſe who judge of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent by what is paſt, will without doubt ſay that the French and Turks have long ago agreed; and that the French Ambaſſador at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> has no greater buſineſs with the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43935:8"/>
               <hi>Ottoman</hi> Port, than to inſtruct him about the Emperors Negotiations in <hi>Hungary,</hi> as a Famous <hi>Venetian</hi> ſaid before me, and that the ſecret intention of the French, is to draw the War into thoſe Provinces of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Hungary,</hi> that remain as yet undivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; to extend, when they ſhall think fit, their Dominions on the other ſide, through the Ruin of Nations, and Deſtruction of Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>However, the French Party every where exclaim, and ask, what advantage can the loſs of <hi>Hungary</hi> produce to <hi>LEWIS THE GREAT?</hi> They ſay on the contrary, the King endeavours to preſerve it in its obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Emperour, and that his Majeſty has given ſufficient Teſtimony of it to the chiefeſt Princes in <hi>Europe;</hi> when <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> being attacked on all ſides, and ready to Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render, he left the Conqueſt of that impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Town, to which he has a juſt Claim, as ſoon as he knew that they were inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Vienna,</hi> by an extraordinary Courrier, that the Turk was bringing all his Forces againſt the Empire, and had ordered his Army to March towards <hi>Belgrade,</hi> with a Deſign to Invade in this War all <hi>Hungary,</hi> and the Neigbouring Provinces to <hi>Auſtria.</hi> That the moſt Chriſtian King had given a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43935:8"/>ſignal demonſtration of his Piety, in not hindring, as very advantagiouſly he could, the Emperour, and the reſt whom the ſame misfortune threatned, from turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their force upon the Enemy, and in withdrawing his Troops that were in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and upon the <hi>Rhine.</hi> We all admired, and highly extolled a Conduct ſo Glorious, ſo Pious, and ſo worthy a great Monarch, that would at ſo high a Rate purchaſe the peace and quiet of Chriſtendom; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt the French that had come after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, had received ſincere Praiſes, if the thing had really been, or but always appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſame they repreſented it to us, but, praiſed be God, the Truth did not always lye hid under the ſpecious pretences with which it was covered.</p>
            <p>I paſs by all examples of paſt ages, and only ſay, that after their actions in theſe latter times, there is no more doubt to be made of their ſiniſter dealings. And to be fully ſatisfied in this point, it is only ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to hear thoſe that are beſt inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the cauſes of this rumour which I ſpread abroad. They ſay, that all their exactneſs in diſcovering of News has not been able to inform them that any acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent had happened which ſhould give occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43935:9"/>to the <hi>Turk</hi> to make a War either in <hi>Aſia,</hi> or <hi>Greece, Theſſaly,</hi> or any of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Provinces; that nevertheleſs at the ſame time they have ſeen in ſeveral Letters of the <hi>French</hi> Emiſſaries, which were diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in <hi>Conſtantinople, Tranſylvania</hi> and <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary;</hi> how that laſt year, on the 30th of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> the War was reſolved upon and ſworn to againſt the Emperour, in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and in the Holy Council, which the <hi>Turks</hi> call <hi>Divan,</hi> in which the Muphti, High Prieſt of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometan</hi> Religion preſided. Which ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently lays open the Authors and Procurers of this War; and clearly ſhews us that the <hi>French</hi> were not aſhamed, as if it had been a famous action in them, to take advice in the <hi>Divan,</hi> and applaud the ſucceſs of the Negotiations, as they did in their Letters writ backwards and forwards to the Rebels, in which they congratulated with them for having drawn the <hi>Turk</hi> to ſuccour them. They promiſe each other in their Letters all the advantages they can expect, which aim at no leſs than to have the Emperour driven out of his beſt Eſtates, and the <hi>Turk</hi> advance into <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> beſtowing Crowns on the one ſide, and rewards on the other, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as every one ſhall have laboured with him for the freeing of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:43935:9"/>
            <p>I lay not the ſtreſs of this upon any falſe rumour that has run among the People; I have aſſured and convincing teſtimonies of it; and the Perſons from whom I take it, deſerve we ſhould make it a point of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience faithfully to believe them.</p>
            <p>Sir, if you ſuſpended as yet your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the <hi>French,</hi> on account of what I have told you; and if you ſhould as yet perſiſt in your belief, that the <hi>Polanders</hi> have had a hand in all this with the <hi>French;</hi> I would deſire you to examine with that juſtice, which in you is uſual, whether what I have related unto you is not ſufficient to raiſe all your ſuſpicions.</p>
            <p>There is no body but knows that in laſt years aſſembly, our illuſtrious <hi>Hungarians</hi> loudly proclaimed, that ſuch of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men, as have been forced to retire to other Places, lived only upon ſuch ſupplies of Mony, as they received from the <hi>French;</hi> that they would not make their Peace with the Emperor, whoſe Clemency extended but juſt ſo far as to offer it, and that they were reſolved to proſecute their enterprize, upon aſſurance of the Promiſes that were made them. So afterwards <hi>Akakia</hi> renewed and confirmed more powerfully than ever the League and Alliance with the Malecou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43935:10"/>of <hi>Tranſilvania.</hi> We alſo ſaw the <hi>French</hi> Emiſſaries without any ſhame of violating the Law of Nations, and in Countries of the ſolemn Treaty of Peace; though they had been manifeſtly diſcovered in a ſecret Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, run on afterwards more then ever, with an unparallelled Impudence, as if all things had been lawful to them.</p>
            <p>You that know me, may well imagine what a trouble it was to me, to ſee that <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> my Country, ſhould be the Theatre where all theſe Villanies were acted, and not one <hi>Polander</hi> to be found who might unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the World.</p>
            <p>Yet the Emperor, with his ordinary Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſuffered the Malecontents of <hi>Hungary</hi> to paſs the next Water with as much quiet and ſecurity as they would deſire, to the end to draw them by this affectionate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct to lay down Arms, return to their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and live peaceably in their Country un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der obedience; and I thought they would then for ever have left their Rebellion, if the Artifices of the French had permitted them to take good counſel.</p>
            <p>We have been inform'd, how 100000 Florins were ordered at <hi>Paris</hi> to foment the Diſcontent of the Rebels in <hi>Hungary,</hi> and quicken the <hi>Turks</hi> the more; How this Sum
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43935:10"/>was delivered at <hi>Dantzick,</hi> the Metropolis of Royal <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> and put into the Hands of a Banker, whoſe Name is <hi>Fromontius,</hi> who afterwards delivered it to the French Emiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, at ſeveral payments, the better to hide the buſineſs. Moreover, we knew, how the <hi>Sieur du Vernay Boucauld,</hi> Count <hi>Teckely</hi>'s real Spy, cauſed to be delivered into the hands of the Sieur <hi>Valentin Nemeſſan,</hi> 11300 Ducats, to oblige the Malecontents to take Arms again, and attack the Cittadel of <hi>Zat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar,</hi> after the French faſhion, with gilt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, I mean, to endeavour to gain the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, or Citizens, with money.</p>
            <p>You knew, Sir, that in <hi>Poland,</hi> we highly diſapproved of this Conduct, which was not totally unknown. The Principal Officers of our Court, before the whole Court, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the moſt Chriſtian King's Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour, that we would no longer allow of ſuch things. We told them, that by order of the whole Senate, we forbid the French to act, as we underſtood they lately had done, upon pain of our King's diſpleaſure. <hi>Monſieur de Vitry</hi> endeavoured to excuſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he produced his Book, aſſuring us, that we ſhould not find in all his Accounts that the Malecontents in <hi>Hungary</hi> had touched the money we ſpoke of, and which was all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43935:11"/>delivered by his Order. Thus it is that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and Craft hide the Truth under falſe pretences.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding you muſt know, that the French Money went into <hi>Hungary,</hi> and men have been employed on purpoſe to ſtop it; and even the very Women have not been ignorant of the Wiles and Practiſes of the French.</p>
            <p>The Princeſs <hi>Radrivilliana,</hi> Widow to the Prince of that name, expreſly forbid the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering any French to paſs through her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>Sacolia,</hi> bordering upon <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> fearing leſt they ſhould, as in other places, corrupt the People with mony. Nevertheleſs the French, whether it was that they would venture all, or whether they thought they were ſufficiently diſguiſed not to be known, took their Journey through this Princeſs's hereditary Country, and one that was taken was carried to her Caſtle, whom ſhe impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, loaded with Irons, and afterwards cauſed to be ſeverely puniſhed. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>De Vitri,</hi> as well as all the Court, ſaw this man run backwards and forwards, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obliged to take another way. This ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Princeſs's Example may convince the World that there were thoſe in <hi>Poland,</hi> who condemned the abominable practiſes of the French.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:43935:11"/>
            <p>All the world would have thought, that after this the <hi>Sieur de Vernay</hi> and all his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Spies would have grown circumſpect by the puniſhment of their Companion, or that at leaſt they would have learnt to conceal themſelves better. But on the contrary, they made it appear by their new behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, that when once a man has gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bounds of Honour he is fit for any thing. Theſe Gentlemen, the Maſters of Perfidiouſneſs, perceived, that they had no fairer a convenience for to entertain a commerce with the French Ambaſſadour at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the Turks, and Malecontents in <hi>Hungary,</hi> than that which they found on the borders of <hi>Poland.</hi> They always had cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence, and had, as often as they could, private enterviews with the Sieurs <hi>Valentin Nemeſſan, Peter Iagel,</hi> and other particular Friends and Allies of <hi>Teckely.</hi> They more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over endeavoured to have ſtill more and more frequent Conferences in <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> ſending firſt one and then another to <hi>Paris,</hi> with the neceſſary Inſtructions of all their Proceedings.</p>
            <p>So the Emperour's Ambaſſadour at this Court, who had notice of all, deſired our moſt Serene King of <hi>Poland,</hi> that his Majeſty would be pleaſed to give order, that no
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43935:12"/>French-man, not being an Ambaſſadour, or bearing ſome other Employment, ſhould be allowed to ſtay in his Dominions. He added to his Entreaty the humble Remonſtrance, that the ancient Treaties ſo often renewed between the Empire and <hi>Poland,</hi> required it for the publick Peace, neither did he omit what he had underſtood concerning the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of the French in <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople.</hi> This occaſioned that the moſt Chriſtian King's Embaſſador was advertized by his Majeſty of <hi>Poland,</hi> to order <hi>Akakia</hi> and <hi>Du Vernay</hi> to withdraw. At the ſame time he received a ſevere Animadverſion about thoſe Peoples Behaviour. The Senate told him, that we were no longer upon terms of conniving, ſince we had been informed, that the French more and more ſtirred up the Troubles of <hi>Hungary,</hi> to draw on a War with the <hi>Turk;</hi> that we knew from good hands what Mony they had given for it, what Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals they had had, and the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> kept every day. We declared that Man was a Spy, and a turbulent Perſon, who had no other buſineſs to detain him about <hi>Leopol,</hi> but only to treat with the <hi>Turks</hi> and Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents, about the means and entring into a League together, for to draw the War in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Hungary;</hi> that therefore we earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43935:12"/>he would cauſe him to retire. The Ambaſſador anſwered, that he would not do what we demanded; he loudly declared, that Monſieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> was ſent with him into <hi>Poland,</hi> to manage the Affairs of the moſt Chriſtian King their Maſter. He preſumed very confidently to deny, that neither the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay,</hi> nor he, had any commerce with the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> or <hi>Turks;</hi> on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, he ſaid, that the French King, in lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> had ſufficiently teſtified how earneſtly he deſired the Peace of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, much leſs to give an occaſion of ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the French of any ſiniſter Deſign. He promiſed however, to take away, as he ſaid, all Suſpitions, that the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> ſhould go to <hi>Varovia,</hi> and that there he ſhould execute his moſt Chriſtian Majeſties commands. However, the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay,</hi> upon the news of all theſe Accuſations, had retired to a Convent of Schiſmatick Monks, of the Order of St. <hi>Baſil.</hi> And this did not put an end to theſe Practices, ſo unworthy the name of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>Some time after, the Emperours Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour diſcovered that new ſums of Mony were come to <hi>Dantzick</hi> for the French. This and many other things which he underſtood at the ſame time, obliged him to renew his Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43935:13"/>to his Majeſty of <hi>Poland.</hi> He had Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the Preſence of the Marqueſs <hi>De Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> the French Embaſſador, and before the whole Senate. He ſpoke a long time, and all his Speech conſiſted of Complaints againſt the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay.</hi> He ſaid, he had only changed the Place, and not his way of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, and ſtill daily continued his Crafts in <hi>Poland.</hi> He produced a Paper he had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the laſt Poſt; by which he was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to underſtand, that the remainder of the Mony the French had engaged for to the Rebels, by the agreement made between them of one hundred thouſand Florins, was lately delivered at <hi>Dantzick.</hi> He ended, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching his Majeſty of <hi>Poland,</hi> to be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed now at laſt to purge his Dominions of thoſe dangerous and ſeditious Men, who by all means fomented the Troubles of <hi>Hungary.</hi> He ſaid, the Miſeries of <hi>Hungary</hi> would reach <hi>Poland,</hi> ſince the Toleration they had, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Violation of the Treaty of Peace, till now always inviolably obſerved. He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, if we gave not ſatisfaction to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, he ſhould be obliged to publiſh in all Princes Courts, and would make known to all <hi>Europe,</hi> that the <hi>French,</hi> by their abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Methods and Practiſes, are the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of the Troubles of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvania,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:43935:13"/>and cauſe of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> War. That they have ſacrificed to their hatred, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy againſt the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the beſt purchaſed Provinces of the Empire, in which they have exerciſed their Treacheries and Treaſons. That they have done all this to make good their ground in the Provinces they have torn from the Empire, and which they cannot retain by any other lawful right. In a word, that their aim in all theſe Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings is only to renew the Treaty of Peace, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pretence that we have broke it, to the end they may the better retain their Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations, and have an occaſion of ſeizing what is left of the Empire.</p>
            <p>This Speech was convincing, and we could do no leſs than to preſs anew the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour to oblige the Sieur <hi>de Vernay</hi> to depart <hi>Poland:</hi> We told him from the King and Senate, that we would no longer be ſatisfied with the vain preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he alledged to detain him. Then Monſieur the Marquis <hi>de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itry</hi> declared, (which he durſt not do the laſt time) that Monſieur <hi>Du <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ernay Boucauld,</hi> was joint Embaſſadour with him from the <hi>French</hi> King. He came thus far to ſave him by the quality of Embaſſadour, ſheltering him under the Law of Nations.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:43935:14"/>
            <p>This Declaration ſtopt our <hi>Polander's</hi> mouths; they thought no more of demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the departure of him that was the real Author of the Rebellion of <hi>Hungary;</hi> and they ſpoke not the leaſt word to put a ſtop to his licentiouſneſs by a juſt advice: On the contrary, they promiſed the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, that the Sieur <hi>Du <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ernay,</hi> his pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Companion, ſhould have all liberty to act for his Maſter.</p>
            <p>This ſoft and complying behaviour of the <hi>Polanders</hi> cannot be better excuſed, than by ſaying, that without doubt they remembred upon this occaſion, that the <hi>French</hi> of late years, make no greater com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, than when their Embaſſadours or Agents, that have liberty in all Countries, are touched, though never ſo ſlightly.</p>
            <p>(Theſe are the words of <hi>Charls Paſcal,</hi> a <hi>French-man,</hi> in his Treatiſe he made of Embaſſies.) "And they do like the Wolfs, who draw the Sheep far from the Shepherd, that they may afterwards devour them. In fine, it is upon theſe frivolous accuſations, that the <hi>French,</hi> to have ſome pretence for making War, have at other times ſo loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly complained, and not long ſince, againſt <hi>Germany,</hi> ſaying, They obſerved not the law of Nations, and broke the moſt ſacred
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43935:14"/>bonds of Humanity, and the Peace to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Embaſſadors. Yet at the ſame time, they paſſed by and endured, without one word ſpeaking, the horrid injuries and moſt barbarous uſage their Embaſſadours received at the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Port.</p>
            <p>I muſt needs tell you here, Sir, that if you wonder that we ſuffer the <hi>French</hi> Emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries in <hi>Poland,</hi> under the pretended quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of an Embaſſadour; we have much more reaſon to admire in <hi>Poland</hi> that the <hi>French</hi> are received in the principal Courts in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> with great kindneſs and ſatisfaction, notwithſtanding there is ſo much reaſon to miſtruſt their intentions.</p>
            <p>This makes me think, dear Sir, that even at this day we might ſee the obſervance of the Laws, the love of your Country, the love and reſpect due to the Emperour, in which you were ſo exact the laſt age, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt amongſt you, if the French had not been the firſt in changing this good order, by conjuring with the <hi>Turks.</hi> Then, 'tis true, a Law made in a Diet was publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Germany;</hi> by which all ſort of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with the <hi>Turks,</hi> and the <hi>French,</hi> their Confederates, was forbidden through the whole Empire; to hinder the ſprouting of the ſeeds of Diviſion and Rebellion,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43935:15"/>which that perfidious Nation caſts where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is admitted. Since no <hi>French</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour was admitted in any one Court in <hi>Germany,</hi> ſo little did they truſt the <hi>French;</hi> and ſcarce would the Princes of the Empire receive Letters from that Count try. Now things are much changed, and we may well cry, when we ſee the preſent miſeries of <hi>Germany, O tempora! O mores!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet all the World has not the ſame opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the French. But to convince you, I will give you an example ſo much the more to be imitated, becauſe it would be extremely advantagious to <hi>Germany,</hi> if the ſame were done there. It happened in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> The Caſtellan of <hi>Primiſtau,</hi> percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that neither his Majeſty of <hi>Poland,</hi> not the Senate expelled the French Spies, and moreover that their deſigns always ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded better and better, and that they were going to deſtroy, by the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> War they were drawing on, a million of innocent Chriſtians, refuſed to permit the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> to enter his Village of <hi>Nimirovia,</hi> and aſſembled a number of men to oblige him to paſs another way; ſo much did he fear this man, of whom he had heard ſo many things.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:43935:15"/>
            <p>There wanted not for great complaints The Marquis <hi>de Vitry</hi> was highly incenſed, and ſought all ways of revenge. And as he is the Moſt Chriſtian King's Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, went directly to Court, to lay before his Majeſty of <hi>Poland,</hi> after his own faſhion, the affront and indignity, offered contrary to the Law of Nations, to his Companion, the Sieur <hi>du Vernay;</hi> and was ſo bold as to demand that the Caſtellan ſhould be impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned for ſatisfaction. The King could not endure this confidence, and told him very harſhly, That it was to no purpoſe to couch the Sieur <hi>du Vernay</hi> under the quality of Ambaſſadour, that the Tragedies he acted under the vain pretence of an Embaſſy were well known; that all the devices of the French, and their contracts with the Turk were diſcovered; that the places where <hi>Akakia</hi> and <hi>du <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ernay</hi> had Conferences were named; their reſolutions and deſigns known; that we could exactly tell how much Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney was ſent from <hi>France</hi> to <hi>Hungary;</hi> and how they had uſed violence, deceit, and wicked practices againſt the Emperour, to the misfortune of Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>The Ambaſſadour would have cleared himſelf of thoſe things, with which, he ſaid, we wrongfully charged his Nation. He
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43935:16"/>thought there was no body could convict the French of their actions in this Country. But the King, who grew hot, would not hear him. He only told him, he would lay 10000 Piſtols with him, that we would prove undeniably all that he had ſaid:</p>
            <p>I tell you nothing here, Sir, but what I have ſeen and heard, and if you had been preſent, you would have thought with me, you had heard <hi>Cicero</hi> ſpeak in the Roman Senate, inſtead of the King of <hi>Poland. How, long,</hi> Catiline, <hi>will you abuſe our patience? How long ſhall your fury ſport at us? to what end will your impudence come? are you igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that all your Deſigns are known to us? don't you perceive that all my Citizens are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the Conſpiracy you carry on with the Malecontents of</hi> Hungary <hi>and the</hi> Turks?</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs <hi>de Vitry</hi> preſſed no farther for the liberty of the French Agents. He did not, like <hi>Catiline,</hi> pray we ſhould not enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain thoſe thoughts of him and his, which no Body believ'd; that when <hi>Hungary</hi> were loſt, we ſhould have need of the French. He look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed like one aſtoniſhed at this blow. He ſtood amazed, and his ſilence ſufficiently confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the thing. All the other French that were preſent, in a conſternation, fixed their Eyes upon the ground, and lifted them not up but
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43935:16"/>to look upon each other, as it were accuſing themſelves. So certain it is, that the inward ſting of Conſcience, and the ſecret power of Truth, daſhes the moſt fierce and confident, and by reducing the guilty to a ſhameful ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, forces them to make ſome ſort of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their Crimes.</p>
            <p>Sir, Here you have a very acceptable Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory to tell ſuch of your Countrymen as can well praiſe all the French actions, whether good or bad. Next, you may ask them, whether they expect a good Peace with the French, becauſe they ſo highly extoll the advantages and pleaſures of Peace.</p>
            <p>If the Ghoſt of the Emperour <hi>Tiberius</hi> ſhould come from Hell, and appear in your aſſembly of the States of the Empire, how juſtly would he blame you, and ſay, <hi>O men, born to ſlavery! will your ſoftneſs extend ſo far as not to believe, but that we only imagine what is done openly in ſight of the whole world, which we ſee, and even feel.</hi> This I ſay, becauſe I know there are ſome amongſt you, that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently miſtruſt the French, to know what they are to think of them, whether they ſuſpect them for not obſerving the Peace, or for entring into a League with the <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I alſo believe, which is much better, that there are many <hi>Germans,</hi> who will talk
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43935:17"/>boldly of taking away the ſnares that are laid for them, and endeavouring to defend the liberty of their Country. I ſtill remember what I ſaw in <hi>Germany</hi> when I travelled in it. At leaſt I doubt not, but that if you would Unite your ſelves to re-eſtabliſh the glory of <hi>Germany,</hi> and retain the valour of your Anceſtors, you might live at home like Kings, and laugh at thoſe who have made themſelves ſlaves to <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what ſide muſt be taken in ſo great a diverſity of Opinions, and among ſo many occaſions of fear on both ſides. My opinion is little to the purpoſe, but if you will believe me, you would judge, that you have moſt reaſon to fear what threatens you from the Eaſt, than from any other place. For what can you expect from a War with the <hi>Turk</hi> but the total ruine of your Goods, and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deſtruction of your Countrey. There is an end of your Liberty, your Religion, your Life, and all you can loſe in this World.</p>
            <p>So that ſince you have ſtill time to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what you are to do, imagine ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times your Churches, your Houſes, your Wives, your Children and your Country, coming to you and conjuring by all they have deſerved from you, that you will not leave them as a prey to your common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43935:17"/>and to prevent the Miſeries of a cruel ſlavery that threatens their Liberty.</p>
            <p>If you will ſay that <hi>Hercules</hi> himſelf wont encounter two; that therefore you muſt treat with the French at any rate. You may ſtill think, if you pleaſe, that the Kingdom of <hi>Hungary</hi> is of far greater value and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, as being the bulwark of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, than the City of <hi>Strasburg.</hi> That at preſent you muſt behave your ſelf like a prudent Pilot in a Storm, who chuſes rather to caſt his Merchandiſe into the Sea, than venture loſing all, by endeavouring to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all. But I muſt alſo tell you, that you have reaſon to fear, leſt under thoſe beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Leaves, a Snake lyes hid. You muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the French have ſtirred up the <hi>Turks.</hi> And theſe ſhall no ſooner have entred <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> beſieged <hi>Vienna,</hi> as without doubt they will beſiege it, deſtroyed all the Country round it; and finally reduced <hi>Germany</hi> to the laſt Extremities; but the French, invited by your Prayers, will voluntarily come of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you their Service. But inſtead of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to quench the Fire, they will bring Oyl to make it the fiercer.</p>
            <p>Sir, I ſhall not ſay many other things that I think about this matter. I only add, that methinks I ſee a Hiſtory, almoſt the ſame
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43935:18"/>with that we read of a Roman Emperor, who had a Fancy to ſet on fire the four corners of <hi>Rome</hi> for the Pleaſure, as he ſaid, of ſeeing a Fire equal to that of <hi>Troy;</hi> and thereby to have an occaſion of doing good to the miſerable Citizens, who would come to complain of their Miſeries and Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes. Perhaps <hi>Nero,</hi> in this cruel Scene, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired nothing but the Glory of building a new City, and calling it by his own Name.</p>
            <p>If you believe me, endeavour above all things to take away the Snares that are laid for you. The French King, as all other Chriſtian Princes, is obliged to defend you againſt the <hi>Turks;</hi> and you will have ſo little trouble in obtaining of it, that he has already agreed upon it with your Enemy. But what will be the event? You will infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly come to complain of one another, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome will be contented, and others diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied; Whilſt you are taken up in theſe Diſputes, the French will do their Work, and at laſt you will find your ſelves under their Dominion, caſt down, conquered and made Slaves without daring to ſay ſo.</p>
            <p>Do not then ſtay to diſpute Rights and Intereſts, till the time when the noiſe of Arms and the fury of War will hinder you from hearing the Law. Be the <hi>Horatii,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:43935:18"/>and not the <hi>Curatii</hi> of your Country. In fine, remember that the members ſeparated from the Head languiſh away like Carcaſſes. Be faithful to your Soveraign, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, your lawful Prince: He has aſcended the Throne by a right owned by all the World; he has always upheld himſelf with Glory; you are uſed to obey him, and he always applied himſelf to your preſervation. You ought to pay him all ſorts of reſpect, if you expect in him a Protector and Father, and if you fear drawing the wrath of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven on your heads. What light would the Planets have if they darkned the Sun? If you prefer the Moon hid under the <hi>Flower-de-Luces</hi> before the Sun at which your <hi>Eagle</hi> looks; if you had rather be ſlaves to the <hi>French</hi> King, than obey the Emperour, all things will happen worſe and worſe to you; and you will draw all the Cruelty of the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians on you, as a puniſhment of your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury and breach of Faith.</p>
            <p>You are not ignorant of the reproach that we caſt upon you, <hi>viz.</hi> that the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> are the only people that deſire to be ſubject to a Foreign Government, and have no love for their Country. That reproach cannot juſtly be retorted upon us; and <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> ſhall ever find in the <hi>Polanders</hi> all ſort
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43935:19"/>of friendſhip and ſervice. We foreſee the dangers that threaten us, and ſeeing of it, our Fore-fathers example, our promiſed Faith, and our natural inclination, ſtir us up powerfully to the defence of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
            <p>Sir, I know, that to make you ſenſible of all that my Friendſhip and ſincerity has made me ſay, I need only repreſent it to you. It only remains that I deſire you to tell me your Opinion with the ſame free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that I may be delivered from the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſs the ſight of the preſent Evils, and the fear of thoſe that threaten us, has put me into. It is time you ſhould read the pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces I ſend you. Farewel.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at my Caſtle <date>
                     <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1. 82.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:43935:19"/>
            <head>The Speech of <hi>Monſieur Zerowiski,</hi> the Emperour's Embaſſadour in <hi>Poland.</hi> Spoken in the Royal Palace before his Majeſty of <hi>Poland,</hi> and in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Princes, Noblemen, and Embaſſadors at that Court; at <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voravia,</hi> the <hi>6th</hi> of <hi>October, 1682.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Great King,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AMongſt other Books, I have hit upon that of the Life and Exploits of Cardinal <hi>Commendon</hi> who was ſent to this Court by the <hi>Pope,</hi> with the Quality of extraordinary <hi>Legate,</hi> in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of <hi>Sigiſimond,</hi> and Reign of <hi>Henry de Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lois:</hi> I have obſerved in it, that it was that Cardinal's Maxim, Never to anſwer but with an affected Silence and Contempt, to all that his Enemies could do or ſay againſt him. Without doubt, in his time, the ſtate of Affairs, the Cuſtoms and Spirits were very different from what they now are; at leaſt, a long experience has made me judge them very different; and I know I cannot, without great diſadvantage, conceal or connive at a thing that very much troubles me. I have underſtood that the French King's Miniſters, publiſhed ſome dayes ago, certain Letters, which brought, as it were, aſſured Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, that His Imperial Majeſties Envoy's only. Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Court was to endeavour, by all poſſible means, to turn the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Armies againſt <hi>Poland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no Body but ſees, and your Majeſty muſt needs perceive, how injurious this is to the Empire; and to what end it is done. They give this out to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unite Two Kingdoms; both which, at this preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture of Affairs, have their chief Intereſt in being firm<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43935:20"/>united. But the Letters took not ſo great an effect as they expected. The Spirits of this Court, were not ſo credulous as to believe them. They are too well ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in <hi>Poland,</hi> of the Piety and Affection of thoſe of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> to think that the Emperor, my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, gives his Embaſſadors ſuch baſe and unworthy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions. There is no Body here that can doubt that his Imperial Majeſty, would be as ſenſible of the loſs of <hi>Poland</hi> as of <hi>Hungary,</hi> ſince it is as much his Intereſt to preſerve the one as the other.</p>
            <p>I come not hither, great King, to tell you what through my Averſion, I could publiſh upon little Rumours that have been ſpread among us; I bring your Majeſty thoſe things, which I can beyond all diſpute, produce before the whole World, as the true Originals of Letters and Anſwers, which the moſt Chriſtian King's Embaſſador, Monſieur <hi>Du Vernay Boucauld,</hi> who is here preſent, has writ to Count <hi>Tekely,</hi> the Head of the <hi>Malecontents,</hi> or received from him. Theſe will evidently diſcover to your Majeſty, what Affairs Mounſieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> has Treated about, with ſo much ſecreſie and circumſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Count <hi>Tekely;</hi> and the reaſon he had ſo cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to conceal from you the Commiſſion he had in this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>I humbly intreat your Majeſty to remember how ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly I intreated you, to remove the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> from your Court and Dominions, as a man pernicious to the Empire, and <hi>Poland.</hi> You would have, Great King, invincible Proofs and Teſtimonies of what I rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; Here they are, ſuch as you will wiſh for, and I am perſuaded they will be ſufficient to make you judge the ſpeedy departure of Monſieur <hi>Du Vernay,</hi> out of your Kingdom, very neceſſary. But I fear, troubling your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty with a long Diſcourſe; I paſs by a thouſand things which I could add; this Memorial is enough, To you I preſent it with all imaginable reſpect.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="memorial_speech">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:43935:20"/>
            <head>A <hi>Memorial</hi> preſented to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> by Monſieur <hi>Zero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wisky,</hi> the Emperour's Reſident.</head>
            <head type="sub">Which was read in the preſence of his Majeſty of <hi>Poland,</hi> and before the Princes and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of his Court; at <hi>Tavoravia,</hi> the 6th of <hi>October,</hi> 1682.</head>
            <p>SInce the laſt <hi>Memorial</hi> which I had the Honour to preſent to your Majeſty, I have endeavoured, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Advice of the Illuſtrious Lords of the Senate, to furniſh my ſelf with ſome piece that might evidently ſhew what Correſpondence the <hi>French</hi> King's Agents have in your Kingdom with Count <hi>Tekely,</hi> Head of the Malecontents in <hi>Hungary.</hi> Theſe wanted alſo to inform you, what Bargains and Agreements paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, which, as I ſaid, tend to the breaking off the Peace and Treaties, that are between your Majeſty and the Emperor, my Maſter. You could not eaſily be informed of it from any but my ſelf. I know the <hi>French</hi> King's Miniſters daily aſſur'd your Majeſty, that they had a Hand in no ſuch thing; and that we accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them falſely. And the French would no longer be ſuſpected to have any ill Deſign againſt the Empire, after the Declaration the French King had made, at the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Bloccade of <hi>Luxemburg.</hi> His moſt Chriſtian Majeſty would inform all <hi>Europe,</hi> how he behaved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in that occaſion; and they were careful to carry his Declaration to all the Courts of the chief Chriſtian Princes. The French King plauſibly declares, that having been informed of the Deſigns which are carrying
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43935:21"/>on in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> againſt the Empire, he would put nothing in Execution which might hinder his Imperial Majeſty, and the moſt Auguſt Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> from oppoſing the <hi>Turks</hi> with all their Forces, and providing for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good of Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>This could by no means allow your Majeſty to believe, that the <hi>French</hi> were in League with the Malecontents and <hi>Turks;</hi> and that they contributed to the taking and plundering the Towns of <hi>Hungary;</hi> for that appeared to be quite contrary to ſuch fair Declarations: But God, the Defender and Revenger of Chriſtians, has ordered thoſe things to fall into my hands, which I lay at the foot of your Majeſties Throne; and which I lay before the Eyes of the whole World. Theſe are the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi>'s Letters, and Correſpondence with Count <hi>Tekeley;</hi> which you will find diametrically oppoſite to thoſe Declarations, ſo worthy the Piety and Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the moſt Chriſtian King.</p>
            <p>I have made uſe of no evil practice for the obtaining theſe Letters: I have not, though I could have done it, ſo much as employed any Body to obſerve the <hi>French.</hi> And to tell you all, I got theſe Letters by the means of the Steward of the moſt Illuſtrious Lord <hi>Stadnick</hi>'s Eſtate. The Sieur <hi>Du Vernay,</hi> after having long im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned the Monks of a Monaſtery of St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> went alſo to importune the Steward, who is <hi>Caſtellan</hi> at <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſlaw.</hi> So much he did, that he ſtirred up the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans Anger againſt himſelf, and ſo conſequently he became my Friend, and has ever ſince been very favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to my Intentions. This <hi>Caſtellan,</hi> ſome dayes ago, ſtopt certain <hi>Hungarians</hi> coming back from <hi>Nimiravia,</hi> whither they went to ſee the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay;</hi> immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acely he ordered them to be brought to me, with the Letters he found about them. I preſently took care to convey them to the Emperour, my Maſter's Territories; ſending at the ſame time the Letters, to the end that all the World might judge, whether I had not juſt cauſe to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43935:21"/>ſuſpect, that the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> exceeded his Maſter's orders.</p>
            <p>Certainly, this Agent, this Miniſter, this Spy, this Ambaſſador, I know not what to call him, but I mean Monſieur <hi>Du Vernay,</hi> has committed a great outrage againſt all Chriſtendom. Againſt the Emperor, in fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting and contriving what he has againſt him. Againſt your Majeſty, in entertaining a Commerce ſo unworthy, ſo pernicious, and for ſo long a time, without your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and in your Kingdom, as if he had been at home. I muſt add, for the Intereſt of your Kingdom, that this Conduct has given the World occaſion to believe, that the <hi>Polanders</hi> were blind enough, not to ſee the dangers their Neighbours made them fear, and that they would themſelves drive the Poniard to their own Breaſt, in permitting the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> to live amongſt them. His proceeding will, without doubt, appear very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to the French King; for that Poſterity may judge and believe, that the great King, <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV, Authorized or commanded, what the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay,</hi> his Agent did in his Name.</p>
            <p>Your Majeſty will not take it ill, that we have diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the Aſſemblies at <hi>Francfort</hi> and <hi>Ratisbonne,</hi> the Famous Exploits of the French, with the Turks and Rebels of <hi>Hungary,</hi> in your Kingdom, which for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ages has been cloſely united with the Auguſt-Houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> and has alwayes acknowledged its own Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, to preſerve <hi>Hungary</hi> to the Empire, thinking it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for <hi>Poland</hi> to ſubſiſt if <hi>Hungary</hi> ſhall fall.</p>
            <p>It is now a year, that the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> travels up and down ſeveral Parts of your Majeſties Dominions, on the Borders of <hi>Hungary.</hi> He always pretends his Maſters, as if we could ſee that <hi>Dantzick</hi> or <hi>Rogioment,</hi> which are the Places the French come through, were not nearer and more proper to receive what Orders the French King would ſend. But he ſtays there to obſerve the nearer the Affairs of <hi>Hungary;</hi> It may be alſo, to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43935:22"/>be in a better condition to go give Count <hi>Tekeley</hi> joy, and to get the reputation with him, of the Progreſs the Turks, by his means, might make in that Country.</p>
            <p>I deſire your Majeſty, that after you have ſeen the Memorial I preſent; and after you are convinced of all the Arts the French have uſed in this Kingdom, you will be pleaſed to order the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> to depart your Dominions, ſince he abuſes his Employments to the prejudice of all Chriſtendom; and renders himſelf unworthy the Protection the Law of Nations allows.</p>
            <p>You may do it ſo much the more juſtly, great King, becauſe the Roman Catholick Church, your Mother, eſteems them as Excommunicated Perſons, who ſide with Infidels, whether it be carrying them Arms, or treating with them.</p>
            <p>The Sieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> has drawn this upon his own head, and if he is puniſhed according to his deſerts, the moſt Chriſtian King will baniſh him his Kingdom, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding his Orders, and engaging his Maſter's Honour and Reputation. In fine, he has committed his Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in the French King's Name, and broke his Maſter's word; acting in all things contrary to the obſervance of it, which if it ſhould fail in the World, could be no where found but in the Mouth of a King or Prince.</p>
            <p>I doubt not, great King, but all my preſſing, reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated and juſt inſtances, will at laſt take effect. The Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liances and Treaties that are between this Kingdom and the Empire, require it from your Majeſty. And I alſo, with a moſt profound reſpect, beg to be admitted to the honour of ſome part of your Affections,</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:43935:22"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> Letter <hi>from Monſieur</hi> Du Vernay, <hi>to Count</hi> Emery Tekeley.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received with great joy the Letters, you did me the honour to write to me, from the Camp before <hi>Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leck,</hi> encloſed in the Pacquets of our Ambaſſadors at <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> nevertheleſs, I was a little ſurprized, that you ſhould ſeal them before he had ſeen them. I wonder alſo, you ſaid nothing about the Siege of <hi>Filleck.</hi> However, I doubt not but that place, by this time, is in your power. Monſieur <hi>Jaygel,</hi> I believe, knows by my laſt Letters, that I have ſeveral times endeavoured to ſend him what I promiſed, and let him have what I have received, but I always wanted an opportunity. When you ſend any of your People to me, order them not to come to my Houſe but at Night, to the end we may do our buſineſs without any bodies knowledge. But what I moſt earneſty deſire is, that above all things, they take care not to follow the Road that goes directly from <hi>Tavoravia</hi> to <hi>Nimirovia.</hi> For here are ſeveral Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Gentlemen, who, by the moſt Serene King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s Order, ſearch, viſit, and detain all ſtrangers that paſs. The ſafeſt way, in my Opinion is, that they leave <hi>Premiſlaw</hi> and <hi>Toreſlavia</hi> on the righ hand, and follow the Road that leads to <hi>Sandomiria,</hi> leſt they be ſeen to enter <hi>Nimirovia,</hi> where I am ſurrounded with Spyes. I recommend the encloſed to you; and deſire you to ſend them according to their Directions, by the firſt opportunity. I will take the ſame care in all things, you ſhall be pleaſed to command me. I am moſt cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sir, <hi>Your moſt zealous Servant,</hi> Du Vernay Boucauld.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Nimirovia,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Sept.</hi> the 22d. 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:43935:23"/>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>The Superſcription was thus: <hi>To the moſt Illuſtrious Lord, Count</hi> Emery Tekeley, <hi>Lord of</hi> Keſmark <hi>and</hi> Arve, <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the</hi> Hungarian <hi>Army, that fights for its Country.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Audience being ended, His Majeſty of <hi>Poland</hi> ſaid, he was convinced of the French Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with the Malecontents. He ſhew'd himſelf very angry that the thing had been conceal'd from him. Next day ſome of the chief Officers of his Court, had Order to go and command the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to depart the Kingdom. He ſaid, he would obey his Majeſties Order; but that he earneſty deſired thoſe Gentlemen to give him ſome dayes, that he might take the Coach of <hi>Tranſilvania.</hi> On the other ſide, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror's Reſident uſed all diligence, and with great ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; for Monſieur <hi>Du Vernay</hi>'s Letter-carrier, called, <hi>Kel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>meſchi,</hi> returned to <hi>Nimirovia</hi> before his departure. This Courrier came with thoſe whom <hi>Tekeley</hi> ſent to the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay,</hi> with his Letters; and thoſe of his great Agent and Confident <hi>Jaygel.</hi> Theſe Courriers were ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and the Letters they had intercepted. Theſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were partly writ in Cyphers. Here you will find them ſet down word for word.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter from <hi>Count Tekeley,</hi> to Monſieur <hi>Du Vernay.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Doubt not, but you have made much of Monſieur <hi>Valentine Nemeſſani,</hi> my Envoy. He has alwayes been faithful to me, and very true to my Intereſt. The Recommendations you gave him touching the Affairs he
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:43935:23"/>communicated with you; will, without doubt, be of great Importance to him, with the Moſt Chriſtian King. I am beholding to you for all you have done for him, and ſhall acknowledge it, as occaſion ſerves: It is time I ſhould inform you, of the preſent ſtate of my Affairs. After I had taken <hi>Caſſovia,</hi> and entered ſome Forts about it, I went with the Vizier of <hi>Budas</hi> Troops, to attack the Famous Fort of <hi>Filleck:</hi> The Inhabitants re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, at firſt, to put themſelves under my Protection; but after a fortnights Siege, they came to beg I would admit them to Capitulate; I granted them what they asked; which was, that the Garriſon, and what other Prople there was, ſhould go out, carrying with them as much as they could upon their Backs: Then I raiſed the Fort, in ſight of the Imperial Army, which was hard by in the Mountains. As I am now informed, it is marched away: and having ſacked the Town of <hi>Vieuxſols,</hi> and other places, retires very haſtily. I deſign to follow the Imperialiſts, and drive them far off, to reſtore my Country to its former Liberty. At length the Emperor will be forced to yield by Force, what we beg as a Favour. Heaven has commiſerated my Fortune indeed ſomewhat late; but I alſo hope, it will draw on a greater and more ſpeedy Vengeance. Sir, I will take care to inform you of all my other Affairs; however I deſire you alwayes to ſtand my Friend. I am</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>At the Camp before</hi> Filleck, <date>
                     <hi>Sept.</hi> 18, 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>SIR, Alwayes ready to ſerve you,</hi> EMERY TEKELEY.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>The Superſcription was: <hi>To the Moſt Illuſtrious Lord, Monſieur</hi> Du Vernay Boucauld <hi>Ambaſſador Extraordinary from the French King.</hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:43935:24"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> Letter <hi>from Monſieur</hi> Peter Jaigel, <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of</hi> Caſſovia: <hi>To Monſieur</hi> Du Vernay.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>LAſt Wedneſday we took and raiſed <hi>Filleck:</hi> where above a thouſand <hi>Janizaries</hi> were ſlain. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, the Vizier made all the <hi>Hungarians</hi> that were preſent, and were under the Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania</hi>'s Dominion, be brought before our Illuſtrious <hi>Count;</hi> then all the Eſtates of the upper <hi>Hungary</hi> being aſſembled, Monſieur <hi>Tekeley</hi> was proclaimed King, and confirmed in that Quality by the Great Turk, who ſent him from the Port, a Hat inſtead of a Crown, with a Standard, and Scepter. After the Ceremony, the <hi>Count</hi> very modeſtly refuſed the Title of King: He is ſatisfied with that of Prince Regent of <hi>Hungary:</hi> His Titles are, <hi>Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus Thokolius Princeps, ac partium Regni Hungariae Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus,</hi> &amp;c. After this Election, the Vizier gave him the beſt Troops, to purſue at the Head of the Army, thoſe of the Imperialiſts. <hi>Caprara</hi> having deſerted the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, pillaged the Towns, and abandoned the Forts <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles</hi> and <hi>Zolian,</hi> is at laſt retired, and has taken his way towards <hi>Threnezin.</hi> Sir, we had done ſomething more, but we have not received what you promiſed us, and without that ſupply, we are forced to proceed gently in our Buſineſs. Monſieur <hi>Nemeſſani</hi> is gone to treat of Affairs at the French King's Court. He needs your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions; we have ordered him in all things, to act to your Honour. We will very ſuddenly ſend you an Expreſs; I beg of you for God's ſake, make him up as large a Sum as you can. I alwayes remain, as I ought,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>SIR, Your moſt obliged Servant,</hi> PETER JAIGEL.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Caſſovia,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Sept.</hi> 22d. 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:43935:24"/>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>The Subſcription was: <hi>To the moſt Illuſtrious Lord, Monſieur</hi> Du Vernay Boucauld, <hi>Ambaſſador Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary from the French King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the Emperour's Reſident had the ſecond time produced theſe Letters, and the dayes appointed were expired, his Majeſty of <hi>Poland</hi> ſent word to the Marqueſs <hi>de Vitry,</hi> the French Ambaſſador in <hi>Poland,</hi> to cauſe the Sieur <hi>Du Vernay,</hi> immediately to retire; that he was weary of hearing daily of his new Deſigns. Without doubt, he has obeyed this Order of the King of <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was thought convenient to put in the Letters here, in the ſame manner as they were writ, and this to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ſuch Perſons as are not content without the Original.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Literae Ablegati Gallici <hi>Du Vernay,</hi> ad primarium Rebellium Ductorem <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mericum Thokolium.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ILluſtriſſime Domine, Domine mihi obſervandiſſime. Scriptas ad me ſeptima hujuſce Menſis ab Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſſima Dominatione Veſtra ex Caſtris ad <hi>Filleck</hi> poſitis Litteras, ſimul cum ad Portam Ottomannicam Oratoris noſtri incluſis, grato animo accepi. Sed non ſine aliquo ſtupore, quod antequam ad ejaſdem manus perveniſſent, reſignatae fuerunt. Miror etiam, quod de 
44<seg rend="above">o</seg> 2<seg rend="above">b</seg> 300<seg rend="above">ſi</seg> 147<seg rend="above">di</seg>. 44<seg rend="above">o</seg> 280<seg rend="above">ne</seg> 187<seg rend="above">Fi</seg> 152<seg rend="above">le</seg> 13<seg rend="above">c</seg> 20<seg rend="above">ki</seg> 9 
Illuſtritas Veſtra nihil ad me. Spero attamen
225<seg rend="above">ja</seg> 42<seg rend="above">m</seg> 362<seg rend="above">ſua</seg> 1<seg rend="above">a</seg> 183<seg rend="above">eſſe</seg>232<seg rend="above">in</seg> 313<seg rend="above">po-</seg> 
374<seg rend="above">te</seg> 48<seg rend="above">s</seg> 373<seg rend="above">ta</seg> 374<seg rend="above">te</seg> 
Ex ultimis meis ad Dominum
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:43935:25"/>
476<seg rend="above">Jaigel</seg>
intelliget
333<seg rend="above">quo</seg> 375<seg rend="above">ti</seg> 164<seg rend="above">es</seg> 319<seg rend="above">pro</seg> 264<seg rend="above">mi</seg> 48<seg rend="above">ſ</seg> 361<seg rend="above">ſo-</seg> 
343<seg rend="above">ru</seg> 22<seg rend="above">m</seg> 187<seg rend="above">fi</seg> 146<seg rend="above">de</seg> 42<seg rend="above">m</seg> 
liberare; &amp; quidquid 
272<seg rend="above">ha</seg> 109<seg rend="above">be-</seg> 
44<seg rend="above">o</seg> 316<seg rend="above">per</seg> 251<seg rend="above">la</seg> 377<seg rend="above">tu</seg> 22<seg rend="above">m</seg> 391<seg rend="above">vo</seg> 255<seg rend="above">lu</seg> 5<seg rend="above">e</seg> 341<seg rend="above">ri</seg> 22<seg rend="above">m</seg> 365<seg rend="above">ſed</seg> 146<seg rend="above">de</seg> 
189<seg rend="above">fu</seg> 9<seg rend="above">i</seg> 49<seg rend="above">t</seg> 359<seg rend="above">ſe</seg> 22<seg rend="above">m</seg> 311<seg rend="above">pe</seg> 47<seg rend="above">r</seg> 303<seg rend="above">occaſio</seg>
Aliquos 
360<seg rend="above">ſi</seg> 166<seg rend="above">ex</seg>
362<seg rend="above">ſu</seg> 9<seg rend="above">i</seg> 48<seg rend="above">s</seg>, 218<seg rend="above">homin</seg> 164<seg rend="above">es</seg> 72<seg rend="above">ad</seg> 263<seg rend="above">me</seg> 264<seg rend="above">mi</seg> 29<seg rend="above">t</seg> 374<seg rend="above">te</seg> 29<seg rend="above">t</seg> 
Illuſtritas Veſtra,
286<seg rend="above">non</seg> 146<seg rend="above">de</seg> 107<seg rend="above">be</seg> 43<seg rend="above">n</seg> 49<seg rend="above">t</seg> 281<seg rend="above">ni</seg> 360<seg rend="above">ſi</seg>
282<seg rend="above">no</seg> 3<seg rend="above">c</seg> 374<seg rend="above">te</seg> 148<seg rend="above">do</seg> 266<seg rend="above">mu</seg> 22<seg rend="above">m</seg> 263<seg rend="above">me</seg> 1<seg rend="above">a</seg> 22<seg rend="above">m</seg> 232<seg rend="above">in</seg> 7<seg rend="above">g</seg> 340<seg rend="above">re-</seg>
147<seg rend="above">di</seg> 50<seg rend="above">u</seg> 49<seg rend="above">t</seg> 232<seg rend="above">in</seg> 48<seg rend="above">ſ</seg> 119<seg rend="above">ci</seg> 9<seg rend="above">i</seg> 48<seg rend="above">s</seg> 298<seg rend="above">om</seg> 281<seg rend="above">ni</seg> 110<seg rend="above">bu</seg> 48<seg rend="above">s</seg>
15<seg rend="above">e</seg> 1<seg rend="above">a</seg> 185<seg rend="above">fa</seg> 119<seg rend="above">ci</seg> 1<seg rend="above">a</seg> 277<seg rend="above">mus</seg>
quae a nobis
262<seg rend="above">ma</seg> 204<seg rend="above">gi</seg> 48<seg rend="above">s</seg>
146<seg rend="above">de</seg> 360<seg rend="above">ſi</seg> 146<seg rend="above">de</seg> 339<seg rend="above">ra</seg> 43<seg rend="above">n</seg> 377<seg rend="above">tu</seg> 47<seg rend="above">r</seg>. 117<seg rend="above">Ca</seg> 389<seg rend="above">ve</seg> 340<seg rend="above">re</seg> 46<seg rend="above">de</seg>
107<seg rend="above">be</seg> 23<seg rend="above">n</seg> 49<seg rend="above">t</seg> 165<seg rend="above">et</seg> 9<seg rend="above">i</seg> 57<seg rend="above">am</seg> 231<seg rend="above">im</seg> 45<seg rend="above">p</seg> 341<seg rend="above">ri</seg> 264<seg rend="above">mi</seg> 48<seg rend="above">s</seg> 280<seg rend="above">ne</seg>
235<seg rend="above">it</seg> 9<seg rend="above">i</seg> 280<seg rend="above">ne</seg> 341<seg rend="above">ri</seg> 359<seg rend="above">ſe</seg> 48<seg rend="above">ſ</seg> 5<seg rend="above">e</seg> 126<seg rend="above">commit</seg> 373<seg rend="above">ta</seg> 23<seg rend="above">n</seg> 29<seg rend="above">t</seg> 233<seg rend="above">quo</seg>
225<seg rend="above">Ja</seg> 383<seg rend="above">va</seg> 342<seg rend="above">ro</seg> 390<seg rend="above">vi</seg> 1<seg rend="above">a</seg> 340<seg rend="above">re</seg> 3<seg rend="above">c</seg> 374<seg rend="above">re</seg> 281<seg rend="above">Ni</seg> 264<seg rend="above">mi</seg> 342<seg rend="above">ro-</seg>
390<seg rend="above">vi</seg> 142<seg rend="above">am</seg>
ducitur,
5<seg rend="above">e</seg> 44<seg rend="above">o</seg> 333<seg rend="above">quo</seg> 14<seg rend="above">d</seg> 362<seg rend="above">ſu</seg> 43<seg rend="above">n</seg> 49<seg rend="above">t</seg> 316<seg rend="above">per</seg>
266<seg rend="above">mu</seg> 41<seg rend="above">l</seg> 375<seg rend="above">ti</seg> 5<seg rend="above">E</seg> 332<seg rend="above">qui</seg> 374<seg rend="above">te</seg> s48
Sereniſſimi Poloniae Regis,
229<seg rend="above">ju</seg> 48<seg rend="above">ſ</seg> 362<seg rend="above">ſu</seg> 166<seg rend="above">ex</seg> 45<seg rend="above">p</seg> 254<seg rend="above">lo</seg> 339<seg rend="above">ra</seg> 376<seg rend="above">to</seg> 340<seg rend="above">re</seg>
48<seg rend="above">s</seg> 1<seg rend="above">a</seg> 332<seg rend="above">qui</seg> 116<seg rend="above">bus</seg> 390<seg rend="above">vi</seg> 1<seg rend="above">a</seg> 376<seg rend="above">to</seg> 340<seg rend="above">re</seg> 48<seg rend="above">s</seg> 298<seg rend="above">om</seg> 280<seg rend="above">ne</seg> 48<seg rend="above">s</seg>
315<seg rend="above">per</seg> 48<seg rend="above">ſ</seg> 13<seg rend="above">c</seg> 343<seg rend="above">ru</seg> 373<seg rend="above">ta</seg> 23<seg rend="above">n</seg> 377<seg rend="above">tu</seg> 47<seg rend="above">r</seg> 146<seg rend="above">de</seg> 375<seg rend="above">ti</seg> 280<seg rend="above">ne-</seg>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:43935:25"/>
23<seg rend="above">n</seg> 377<seg rend="above">tu</seg> 47<seg rend="above">r</seg> 331<seg rend="above">que</seg>.
Exiſtimo
246<seg rend="above">ita</seg> 331<seg rend="above">que</seg> 364<seg rend="above">Secur</seg> 9<seg rend="above">i</seg> 373<seg rend="above">ta-</seg> 
377<seg rend="above">te</seg> 22<seg rend="above">m</seg> 268<seg rend="above">major</seg> 261<seg rend="above">em</seg> 183<seg rend="above">eſſe</seg> 45<seg rend="above">P</seg> 340<seg rend="above">re</seg> 264<seg rend="above">mi</seg> 48<seg rend="above">s</seg> 253<seg rend="above">li</seg> 1<seg rend="above">a</seg> 22<seg rend="above">m</seg>
34<seg rend="above">et</seg> 225<seg rend="above">Ja</seg> 342<seg rend="above">ro</seg> 48<seg rend="above">s</seg> 251<seg rend="above">la</seg> 390<seg rend="above">vi</seg> 1<seg rend="above">a</seg> 22<seg rend="above">m</seg> 72<seg rend="above">ad</seg> 4<seg rend="above">d</seg> 166<seg rend="above">ex</seg> 374<seg rend="above">te</seg> 37<seg rend="above">r-</seg>
75<seg rend="above">am</seg> 340<seg rend="above">re</seg> 253<seg rend="above">li</seg> 23<seg rend="above">n</seg> 330<seg rend="above">qua</seg> 43<seg rend="above">n</seg> 39<seg rend="above">t</seg> 389<seg rend="above">ve</seg> 281<seg rend="above">ni</seg> 160<seg rend="above">en</seg> 374<seg rend="above">te</seg> 48<seg rend="above">s</seg>
72<seg rend="above">ad</seg> 263<seg rend="above">me</seg> 
quaſi,
353<seg rend="above">Sa</seg> 23<seg rend="above">n</seg> 148<seg rend="above">do</seg> 264<seg rend="above">mi</seg> 341<seg rend="above">ri</seg> 1<seg rend="above">a</seg> 22<seg rend="above">m</seg> 374<seg rend="above">te</seg> 280<seg rend="above">ne-</seg>
340<seg rend="above">re</seg> 43<seg rend="above">n</seg> 49<seg rend="above">t</seg> 50<seg rend="above">u</seg> 43<seg rend="above">n</seg> 146<seg rend="above">de</seg> 281<seg rend="above">Ni</seg> 264<seg rend="above">mi</seg> 342<seg rend="above">ro</seg> 390<seg rend="above">vi</seg> 1<seg rend="above">a</seg> 22<seg rend="above">m</seg>
232<seg rend="above">in</seg> 7<seg rend="above">g</seg> 340<seg rend="above">re</seg> 147<seg rend="above">di</seg> 390<seg rend="above">vi</seg> 146<seg rend="above">de</seg> 340<seg rend="above">re</seg> 23<seg rend="above">n</seg> 377<seg rend="above">tu</seg> 37<seg rend="above">r</seg> 332<seg rend="above">Qui-</seg>
1<seg rend="above">a</seg> 166<seg rend="above">ex</seg> 25<seg rend="above">p</seg> 254<seg rend="above">lo</seg> 339<seg rend="above">ra</seg> 376<seg rend="above">to</seg> 341<seg rend="above">ri</seg> 116<seg rend="above">bus</seg> 30<seg rend="above">u</seg> 43<seg rend="above">n</seg> 147<seg rend="above">di</seg> 331<seg rend="above">que</seg>
119<seg rend="above">ci</seg> 43<seg rend="above">n</seg> 13<seg rend="above">c</seg> 377<seg rend="above">tu</seg> 48<seg rend="above">s</seg> 362<seg rend="above">ſu</seg> 22<seg rend="above">m</seg>
Adjunctas Illuſtritati Veſtrae recommendo, ut prima certe occaſione tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittere dignetur. Utar ego paridiligentia in iis omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, quae a me deſiderate poterit. Cum toto animo ſum, &amp; maneo,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Illuſtritati Veſtra</hi> Paratiſſimus ſervus, DU VERNAY BOUCAULD.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Nimiroviae</hi> 
                  <date>22 <hi>Sept.</hi> 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſcriptio Tituli:</hi> Illuſtriſſimo Domino Comiti, Emerico Thokolio: Hereditario in Keſmark &amp; Arva, Exercitus Hungarici pro Patria militantis, Generali, Domino, &amp; Amico mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi Confidentiſſimo, Obſervandiſſimo.</p>
            </postscript>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:43935:26"/>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>Litterae</hi> Thekely <hi>ad</hi> Du Vernay.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Illustriſſime Domine, mihi obſervantiſſime.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NUllus ambigo, quin Illuſtriſs. Dominatio Veſtra Ablegatum meum, Egregium <hi>Valentinum Nemeſſani,</hi> pro ſincero ejuſdem hactenus ſemper declarato erga me affectu &amp; candore, favorabiliter proſecuta ſit, <hi>&amp; negotio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, medio ipſius coram declaratorum, cur ſui, multum ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fficaci ſuae recommendatione, apud Chriſtianiſſimum Gallia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Regem pondus addiderit:</hi> quo nomine obligatum me ad reciprocationem paralis dexteritatis Illuſtriſs. Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationi Veſtrae exhibendae, declaro porro quam rerum faciem progreſſumque res meae habuerint hujuſque Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſs. Dominationi Veſtrae pro debito neceſſitudinis mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuae reſcribendum cenſui. Nempe occupata <hi>Caſſovia,</hi> &amp; Arcibus quamplurimis jugum ſubire coactis, <hi>Budenſi Vizirio</hi> copiiſque Turcicis auxiliaribus <hi>Filekinum</hi> Forta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litium alias famoſcum, nolens protectioni meae ſeſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere, poſt obſidionem ſpatio duarum hebdomadarum toleratam, ad conditiones pacis acceptandas, ſupplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur provolvi (Praeſidiariis &amp; cuncta plebe eo coacta, cum farcinulis, quas quivis humeris ſuis ſuſtentare effereque poterat, libere dimiſſis) compulſum, &amp; conſequenter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rutum eſt, Germano milite in proximo circa montanas oberrante, &amp; haec conniventibus oculis intuente, qui im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par viribus ad reſiſtendum, ſe ex montanis civitatibus (uti rumor eſt recenter allatus) proripuit, &amp; expilata civitate <hi>vetero-Solienfi,</hi> aliiſque locis, regreſſum praecipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare dicitur, quocum fortunae aleam ſubire animus eſt, nec praetermittitur occaſio eundem profligandi, Patriam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que hanc in tranquillum ſtatum priſtinae libertatis repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendi, ut quae Caeſar ſuppliciter rogatus remittere noluit, inventus cedere cogatur, Nemeſi Divina ſortis meae miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a ſero quidem, et eo gravius altionis poenas repeten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:43935:26"/>Quid poſt hac rerum gerendarum occurrerit genui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Illuſtriſſ. Dominationem Veſtram informare haud praetermittam. Me de caetero benevolentiae ejuſdem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendans, maneo.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Illuſtriſſimae Dominationi veſtrae, Ad officia paratus,</hi> EMERICUS THEKELI.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dat. ex Caſtris Hungariris ad Filleck poſitis</hi> 
                  <date>die 18. <hi>Sept.</hi> 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſcriptio:</hi> Illuſtriſſimo Domino Du Vernay Boucauld, Chriſtianiſſimi Regis Galliarum Legato Extraordinario, mihi obſervandiſſimo.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Litterae <hi>Petri Jaigel,</hi> Commendantis Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſovienſis ad <hi>Du Vernay.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Illuſtriſſime Domine mihi colendiſſime,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Praeterito die Mercurii, occupato &amp; deleto Fortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio <hi>Filleck,</hi> ubi pluſquam mille Jenizzarones peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt, poſt hac primum omnibus Hungaris, qui penes Principem Tranſylvaniae fuerant, ad Dominum Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem per Vezirum pulſis, cum ſumma ſolemnitate, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentibus Comitatibus, &amp; univerſis Statibus Regni Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gariae Superioris eſt in Regem electus, &amp; a Turca con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatus, elevatuſque Princeps Comes, cui a Porta pile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, loco Coronae oblatus, item Vexillum &amp; Sceptrum: qui finita electione, recuſavit ſe uti titulo Regis, ſed ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulo Principis, cujus titulus eſt talis: <hi>Emericus Thokoli Princeps, ac Partium Regni Hungariae Dominus, &amp;c.</hi> Fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:43935:27"/>his, ſelectam militiam Vezirus dedit Domino Comiti, ut fugientem Exercitum Germanicum proſequcretur Princeps noſter. <hi>Caprara</hi> depraedatis montanis civitatibus, derelictis Fortalitiis <hi>Vigles</hi> &amp; <hi>Zolian,</hi> diſceſſit &amp; abiit verſus <hi>Thraenezin.</hi> Illuſtriſſ. Domine &amp; majora facere po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuiſſemus, 
ſed quia videmus Veſtrae Illuſtratis
267<seg rend="above">maxim</seg> 1<seg rend="above">a</seg> 319<seg rend="above">pro</seg> s64<seg rend="above">mi</seg> 48<seg rend="above">ſ</seg> 359<seg rend="above">ſa</seg> non adimpleri, &amp; hic ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes mediis, mitius debemus agere.
466<seg rend="above">Nemeſſani</seg> 1<seg rend="above">a</seg> 108<seg rend="above">bi-</seg>  390<seg rend="above">vi</seg> 29<seg rend="above">t</seg> 72<seg rend="above">ad</seg> 4<seg rend="above">Regem</seg> 20<seg rend="above">Galliae</seg>. Neceſſum eſt, ut Veſtra Illuſtritas optime ibi recommendet negotia noſtra, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſum eſt ipſi ut omnia ibi agat cum 
219<seg rend="above">honor</seg> 15<seg rend="above">e</seg> 438<seg rend="above">Illtris</seg> Vrae. Brevi mittemus expreſſum 72<seg rend="above">ad</seg> 438<seg rend="above">Illuſtr.</seg> Veſtram 232<seg rend="above">in</seg> 225<seg rend="above">Ja</seg> 338<seg rend="above">ro</seg> 48<seg rend="above">s</seg> 21<seg rend="above">l</seg> 24<seg rend="above">o</seg> Rogo per amorem Dei 264<seg rend="above">mi</seg> 29<seg rend="above">t</seg> 273<seg rend="above">ta</seg> 29<seg rend="above">t</seg> 215<seg rend="above">ho</seg> 280<seg rend="above">ne</seg> 48<seg rend="above">s</seg> 373<seg rend="above">ta</seg> 22<seg rend="above">m</seg>.
Quotam. Ego interea ſum ſemper, &amp; maneo quiſquis
debeo eſſe, &amp; </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Illuſtritatis Veſtrae</hi> Servus obligantiſſimus PETRUS JAIGEL. 467</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Caſſoviae</hi> 
                  <date>22. <hi>Sept.</hi> 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſcriptio:</hi> Illuſtriſſimo Domino <hi>Du Vernay Boucauld,</hi> Chriſtianiſſimi Regis Galliarum Legato Extraordinario, mihi Colendiſſimo.</p>
            </postscript>
            <pb facs="tcp:43935:27"/>
            <pb n="186" facs="tcp:43935:28"/>
            <pb n="187" facs="tcp:43935:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
